Today's דף *daf* is צדי גמל *Tzadi Gimmel*. We start at the
bottom of צדי בית *Tzadi Beis*, looking at the ציבור *tzibur* as
a יחיד *yachid* טעונין סמיכה te'unin smicha, *te’unin semicha*. So it's about
one, two, three, about ten lines from the bottom. So we're now
moving based on the כל *kol* issue framing of the משניות *mishnayos*.
We had moved on from different questions about the measures, and now
we are talking about the issue of סמיכה smicha? *semicha*, putting hands
on the
קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot*. We look at that line in the משנה Mishnah
*mishna*. כל קרבנות korbanot, היחיד טעונין סמיכה smicha *Kol korbanos hayachid te’unin
semicha*, all individual קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot*. We learned that communal קרבנות korbanot,
*korbanot* are only two basically: the פר *par* for העלם דבר *helam
davar* when בית דין *beis din* rules incorrectly, and then there's a
debate whether the other one is: is it the goat for עבודה
זרה Avodah Zarah. *avodah zarah* when the בית דין *beis din* rules
incorrectly, or is it the one on יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom
Kippur*, the goat לעזאזל *l'azazel*? And everybody agrees that there was an
act of סמיכה smicha. *semicha* on that goat that sent off. We
do that in the עבודה Avodah *avodah* of יום כיפור Yom Kippur?
*Yom Kippur* every יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur*. We say that
in מוסף *Mussaf*. But the question is: is it classic סמיכה smicha?
*semicha* or not, because are the כהנים Kohanim *kohanim* also getting atonement
and are they considered part owners in that so that it should
be seen as classic סמיכה smicha *semicha*? Those were the two communal
קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*, and now we turn to the individual קרבנות Korbanot
*korbanot*. So let's see what it says. כל קרבנות Korbanot היחיד טעונין
סמיכה smicha? *Kol korbanos hayachid te’unin semicha*, all individual קרבנות Korbanot, *korbanot*
get סמיכה smicha *semicha*, חוץ chutz, *chutz* with the exception of בכור
ומעשר ופסח bechor u'maaser u'pesach, *bechor u'ma'aser u'pesach*. From the בכור bechor
*bechor*, מעשר maaser. *ma'aser*, and פסח pesach *pesach*, which is a weird
exception. Meaning you have obligatory קרבן korban *korban*, you have the חטאת
chatas, *chatas* and אשם asham *asham*. You have free will קרבנות Korbanot
*korbanot*, the עולה ola. *olah* and שלמים shelamim, *shelamim*. The only thing
you don't have are these three, which are obligatory בכור *bechor*, מעשר
maaser *ma'aser*, and פסח pesach. *pesach*, but somehow they fall between the
cracks. They're obligatory but קדשים קלים *kodshim kalim*. So let's take a
look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* why not. So here's what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. תנו רבנן Tanu rabbanan. *Tano Rabbanan*, קרבנו korbano,
ולא הבכור *Korbano v'lo habechor*. So it says וסמך ידו vesamach yado,
על ראש קרבנו al rosh korbano, *v'samach yado al rosh korbano*, you
should put your hands on the top of your קרבן korban *korban*,
on the head of your קרבן korban *korban*. So it says his
קרבן korban, *korban* and not a בכור *bechor*.
Because the קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*, the possessive means some not all. שיכול
ולא דין הוא sheyachol v'lo din hu? *sheyakhol v'lo din hu*, because
I could have said a קל וחומר kal v'chomer. *kal v'chomer*. ומה
שלמים shelamim שאין קדושתן מרחם טעונין סמיכה smicha *u'mashelamim she'ein kedushasan merechem
te’unin semicha*, if when you have normal שלמים shelamim *shelamim*, yes we
skipped a little bit to be more on where we should be.
Okay, where we should be? Okay, so we're starting from the two
dots on צדי בית *Tzadi Beis* near the bottom, ten lines from
the bottom. And we're now discussing the issue that individual קרבנות korbanot,
*korbanot* all get סמיכה smicha, *semicha*, whether חטאת chatas. *chatas*, אשם *asham*,
שלמים shelamim *shelamim*, or עולה ola *olah*, with the exception of בכור
*bechor*, מעשר *ma'aser*, and פסח pesach, *pesach*. And we will discuss in
a minute why that is. So here we're going to learn from
the פסוקים pesukim *psukim*. So it says קרבנו korbano, *korbano*, his קרבן
korban. *korban*. You put your hands on your קרבן korban *korban* or
his. He puts his hands on his קרבן korban, *korban*. So that
his קרבן korban *korban* is somehow an exclusionary word, that ו vav
*vav*, his, not all. So ולא הבכור *v'lo habechor*, not a firstborn.
שיכול ולא דין הוא *sheyakhol v'lo din hu*, I could have made
a קל וחומר *kal v'chomer*. ומה שלמים shelamim שאין קדושתן מרחם טעונין
סמיכה smicha *u'mashelamim she'ein kedushasan merechem te’unin semicha*, שלמים shelamim *shelamim* that
are not sanctified from the womb you have to do סמיכה smicha?
*semicha* for them. בכור *bechor*, so the firstborn animal, שקדושתו מרחם *shekedushaso
merechem*, it's even more sanctified, it starts already from the womb of
its mother. You don't even have to do an act of sanctifying
it. So therefore שקדושתו מרחם אינו דין שטעון סמיכה eino din she'te'un
smicha, *shekedushaso merechem ayno din shete’un semicha*, how much more so would
I think you'd have to do סמיכה smicha, *semicha*? תלמוד לומר Talmud
Lomar *talmud lomar*, so therefore the verse says קרבנו korbano *korbano*. It's
a limiting word. This is by שלמים shelamim *shelamim*, which says he
should put his hand on the head of his קרבן korban. *korban*.
So not all things that are like שלמים shlamim *shelamim*. Well, what's
like שלמים shelamim, *shelamim*? A בכור *bechor*. It's קדשים קלים *kodshim
kalim*. It's lighter sanctity, but it's of a different nature. So therefore
that's excluded. קרבנו korbano, ולא הבכור *Korbano v'lo habechor*. Now and then
we go on. קרבנו korbano ולא מעשר v'lo maaser, *Korbano v'lo ma'aser*.
It says קרבנו korbano *korbano* again, and we use that to say
not all things that are like שלמים shelamim *shelamim*, so to exclude
מעשר *ma'aser*, the tenth of every firstborn animal that also is a
קרבן korban, *korban*. שיכול ולא דין הוא *sheyakhol v'lo din hu*. I
would say that it's a קל וחומר *kal v'chomer*. ומה שלמים shelamim.
שאין מקדשין לפניהם ולאחריהם טעונין סמיכה smicha. *u'mashelamim she'ein mekadshen lefanav u'le'acharayv
te’unin semicha*, שלמים *shelamim* do not sanctify before and after them. And
nevertheless you produce סמיכה smicha. *semicha*. What does that mean? If I
sanctify this animal as a שלמים *shelamim*, somehow there's no way that
that קדושה kdusha *kedusha* can transfer to the animal standing right behind
it or right after it. It's only the animal that I directly
sanctify. That's obvious. But we'll see how that contrasts to a בכור
*bechor*. And so by a שלמים *shelamim* you do do סמיכה smicha.
*semicha*. So מעשר שמקדש לפניו ולאחריו אינו דין שטעון סמיכה smicha. *ma'aser
shemekadesh lefanav u'le'acharayv ayno din shete’un semicha*, how much more so מעשר
*ma'aser* which sanctifies before and after should require סמיכה smicha *semicha*. What
does this mean? How would you do מעשר *ma'aser* of your firstborn
animals? You take all your
firstborn animals, all the animals that were born this year, you put
them in a pen, you'd have them walk through single file a
gate, and you'd count one, two, three, four. When you got to
ten, you would hit them with like a stick with some dye
on it, red dye, and that would and you would mark it
and then you would know that that was the tenth and that's
the one you would give as a קרבן korban. *korban*. Now the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* teaches or the משנה Mishnah. *mishna* teaches based on
פסוקים psukim *psukim* that if you miscount and if you counted number
nine and you said ten by mistake when you were up to
nine, or for number eleven you said ten, that those also get
קדושת מעשר *kedushas ma'aser* as well as of course the tenth. You
don't get out of the tenth being מעשר *ma'aser*, but if you're
off by one, then that other one also
becomes. Even though it's not really the מעשר. So that shows some
extra power there, so I might think that how much more so
should you require סמיכה? smicha.
So תלמוד לומר Talmud Lomar קרבנו, korbano your קרבן korban. again said
by שלמים, ולא מעשר, not all קרבנו, korbano not מעשר. One more
exclusion and then we'll discuss the logic behind this.
קרבנו korbano? a third time, and that is excluding that you don't
do סמיכה smicha, in the קרבן פסח. korban pesach. שיכול ולא דין
הוא? It's maybe a קל וחומר. ומה שלמים שאינו בעמוד והיה u'mah
shelamim she'eino b'amud v'haya
טעונין סמיכה, smicha שלמים that there's no obligation to bring, right, you
do it freely. Nevertheless, you require סמיכה. smicha. פסח שהוא בעמוד והיה,
pesach she'hu b'amud v'haya, פסח pesach which is obligatory, אינו דין שטעון
סמיכה, smicha. how much more so should I think you demand סמיכה?
smicha תלמוד לומר קרבנו, korbano so says his קרבן korban ולא פסח,
v'lo pesach, and not the פסח. So okay, it's all very nice,
but at the end of the day חז"ל Chazal are deciding what
to exclude, right? Because there's nothing that specifically although you could say
it's something that is שלמים-like and what else is שלמים-like other than
these? Of course you could have maybe excluded a תודה, toda, but
okay, that I think maybe it's explicit in the פסוקים psukim. I'd
have to check up on that for תודה. toda. Maybe that's why
not. Anyway, so the logic here about why maybe not these? And
again, it's not obligatory versus free will, because you do סמיכה smicha.
by a חטאת, chatas? I mean for, you know, for God's sake
that's the whole thing we do on, you know, on יום כיפור,
that the כהן kohen puts his hands on it, he says the
וידוי. viduy. Right, so what's the logic? You do it on a
free will, you do it on obligatory חטאת ואשם, chatas v'asham, you
don't do it on these obligatory שלמים-like type of things. So there's
a hint to this in the רש"י. Rashi. If you look, oh
no it's in this microscopic רש"י Rashi here. By the way, we're
almost at the next פרק perek we get back to normal רש"י.
Rashi. But anyway, if you take a look at רש"י Rashi says
like this.
One minute, let me just find where it is, ah. Three lines
from the bottom רש"י Rashi says like this. שלוש קרבנו shalosh korbano
it should be not קרבנות, כתיב בסמיכה בשלמים. ksiv b'smicha b'shelamim. קרבנו
korbano שבא לשום ריצוי ודורון, she'ba l'shum ritzui v'doron, a קרבן korban
that is coming for the sake of like appeasing God or as
a gift to God, ולא בכור מעשר פסח v'lo bechor maaser pesach
שאינם באים לריצוי. she'einam ba'im l'ritzui.
On the one hand they're not coming as a type of like,
you know, gift to to further the relationship if you would, as
an offering, אלא חובה הם עליו, ela chova heim alav, they're an
obligation, and on the other hand ולא לכפרה, v'lo l'kapara, they're also
not atoning. What does that mean? What is the purpose of סמיכה?
smicha, We could ask that question. Now, normally I think you'd write
most likely think since it says you should put your hands on
ראש קרבנו rosh korbano and it uses the possessive, that maybe the
idea of סמיכה smicha, is to identify this with the bringer. So
this is your קרבן, korban. you're putting your hands on it, you're
emphasizing the connection. However, if that were true, you couldn't understand why
you should never why there would ever be an exception because you
always want to identify it with yours.
So it seems that that's not how סמיכה smicha. is conceptualized because
there is something that at least comes with סמיכה, smicha. at least
by a חטאת. chatat What comes with סמיכה smicha, by a חטאת?
chatat What do we do on יום כיפור? What is going to
go together with סמיכה? smicha, וידוי, viduy, right? So it could be,
right, and the whole idea by the way we just discussed yesterday
about this שעיר המשתלח, se'ir hamishtale'ach, like the putting the sins on
the head, that's a particular idea of this scapegoat idea but even
without that scapegoat just the normal idea of וידוי viduy is basically
sort of designating the function of this קרבן. korban. You're making your,
you're saying your וידוי, viduy, you're saying your confession, you're putting your
hands on it, you're saying this is somehow, you know, to atone
for my sins. That's the message presumably when you do the סמיכה,
smicha. which is affected by, you know, the physical connection as you're
saying the וידוי. viduy. So the רמב"ם, Rambam, it's not in the
גמרא Gemara but the רמב"ם Rambam says, says יראה לי yeira'eh li
says the רמב"ם, Rambam, it would seem to me that you should
also say something. It's so funny because it's not in any גמרא
Gemara but the רמב"ם Rambam says he would seem to me you
should also say something when you're bringing a שלמים or an עולה.
olah. And he says, I could check I should check the רמב"ם,
Rambam, I think he says you say like words of שבח והודאה,
shevach v'hoda'ah, thanks to God. Okay, which makes sense, you're trying to
sort of designate the function of this type of a קרבן korban,
so you want to have this verbal declaration and you do it
at the time of the סמיכה. smicha, So I think that's a
little bit what רש"י Rashi is getting to, that these things בכור
ומעשר ופסח, it's more like I'm doing it because I have to,
I'm not doing it on my own free will, and it's not
like it's serving as an atonement that I want to sort of
say what my sins are to say that this somehow is going
to atone for those things. So, you know, what type of personal
declaration is meaningful here? Meaning there's nothing personal about my declaration. I'm
doing because you told me I have to, so fine, I'll do
it. But at the sins, I have to, but there's something personal,
which is my sins, what have I sinned? By the שלמים and
the עולה olah there's something personal because I'm opting to give it,
so what do I want to express in the giving? But here
there's nothing personal. Every single person has to give מעשר and בכור
and פסח, so I'm doing what you told me but there's no
specific personal connection. That would be my feeling about what why we're
saying here that there's no that there's no סמיכה. smicha, I should
of course admit, you know, that that it this is helped by
the רמב"ם Rambam who who says that there is a declaration. and
שלמים *Shlamim*, which does not appear in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. But
I do think that that is a little bit of what רש"י
*Rashi* is getting to. On the other hand, you would say, look,
even if you have to, wouldn't you want it also to have
some personal connection, in particular פסח *Pesach*, which is all about like,
you know, sort of כאילו הוא יצא *ke'ilu hu yatza* feeling that
sense of personal connection? But I think that's, I think that's the
way to explain the exclusion here, that חטאת chatat *Chatas* and אשם
*Asham* you're obligated, but there's something personal there which is your sins,
you know, your specific sins, and the other things it's your choosing
to give it so it's what are you trying to express in
your personal desire, and here it falls between those two categories. Yes.
Women making סמיכה smicha *smicha*?
We're about to get to that in the next משנה Mishnah *mishna*.
Okay. So, all right. Let me just see if I can very
quickly just find that רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam*. I'm
sorry, yesterday I intended to come but the weather was like dreadful.
I really didn't feel like coming. I actually had a private session.
I'm afraid of thunder.
Yeah. See? Okay.
It is an unusual רמב"ם *Rambam* because it's like there's no גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. He just felt a need for it for, you know,
for parallel symmetry sake.
Let me just see.
Okay, here it says like this. So he says: כיצד סומך *Keitzad
somech*? So you bring it, you put your two hands. כיצד מתוודה
*Keitzad misvadeh*? How do you do וידוי vidui *viduy*? אומר חטאתי עויתי
פשעתי ועשיתי כך וכך וחזרתי בתשובה לפניך וזו כפרתי *Omer: Chatasi, avisi,
pashati ve'asisi kach ve'kach vechazarti betshuva lefanecha vezu kaparasi*. Okay, which is
interesting. We normally don't hear the end of that sentence not on
יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, right? I'm doing תשובה teshuvah *tshuva*, which is
also interesting, the bringing of תשובה Teshuva *tshuva* into the חטאת chatas,
*Chatas* and the אשם *Asham* because, you know, by in the קרבנות
*korbonot* normally there is a וידוי vidui, *viduy*, but the תשובה Tshuvah
*tshuva* is de-emphasized. The רמב"ם *Rambam* brings the תשובה Tshuvah *tshuva* and
then you actually say וזו כפרתי *vezu kaparasi*. היה קרבן korban שלמים
*Haya korban shlamim*? סומך בכל מקום שירצה מן העזרה במקום שחיטה shechitah,
ויראה לי שאינו מתוודה על השלמים אבל אומר דברי שבח *Somech bechol
makom sheyirtze min ha'azara bimkom shechita veyera li she'eino misvadel al hashlamim
aval omer divrei shevach*. Okay? So he just says it would seem
to me this is what you should be doing. Doesn't say what
you do by an עולה olah *olah*. Maybe by an עולה Oleh
*olah* he would think you do וידוי vidui *viduy* because the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* understands that an עולה Olah, *olah* sometimes is coming for
כפרה Kaparah *kapara* for מצות עשה *mitzvas asei*. But anyway, the רמב"ם
*Rambam* has this idea that you should be saying something for all
the קרבנות *korbonot*. So it does seem that there's this something about
which makes it a personal connection, which is maybe lacking here. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* continues. Okay, קרבנו korbano ולא פסח
*korbano velo pesach*. Two lines from the bottom. איכא למפרך *Ika lemifrach*.
One minute, you could have asked, why could I have thought, why
do I need to exclude these from סמיכה smicha, *smicha*? How would
I have been entitled to apply סמיכה smicha, *smicha* to them? You
know, I can't learn it out from שלמים *shlamim*. מה לשלמים שכן
טעונים נסכים n'sachim ותנופת חזה chazeh ושוק *Ma lishlamim sheken te'unim nesachim
utnuphas chaze veshok*. So, you know, שלמים *shlamim* is different. You have
to, it gets the נסכים *nesachim*, the, you know, the wine and
the מנחה *mincha*, and you wave the חזה chazeh *chaze* and the
שוק shok, *shok*. So maybe, maybe only סמיכה smicha *smicha* by them
and I never would have thought of applying סמיכה smicha? *smicha* to
these other cases. So why do I need to exclude it? So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: You know what, you're right. קרא אסמכתא
בעלמא *Kra asmachto be'alma*. The פסוקים psukim, *psukim* are just an אסמכתא
*asmachta*. I anyway wouldn't, you know, it doesn't say it explicitly, it
only says it explicitly by שלמים *shlamim* and by חטאת chatas. *Chatas*
and אשם *Asham*, so and I don't have a basis for extending
it to these. I don't need a פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* to exclude
it. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: אלא קרא למה לי *Ella
kra lama li*? So then what do I do with all the
קרבנו korbano *korbano*, קרבנו korbano *korbano*, קרבנו *korbano*? To teach me the
following: קרבנו ולא קרבן חבירו Korbano Velo Korban Chaveiro, *Korbano velo korban
chavero*. You can't do סמיכה semichah, *smicha* on somebody else's קרבן korban
*korban*. You have to do סמיכה semichah, *smicha* on your own קרבן
korban *korban*. Okay, which is maybe self-evident. קרבנו ולא קרבן korban. עובד
כוכבים Oveid Kochavim *Korbano velo korban oved kochavim*. A non-Jew's קרבן korban
*korban* does not require סמיכה semichah, *smicha*. That was something that we
taught before. And קרבנו *korbano*...
by the way, תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says or I think רש"י *Rashi*
says תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says that it's, it's not really different than
קרבן חבירו korban chaveiro, *korban chavero*. Once you assume that a non-Jew
can't enter the בית המקדש beit hamikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*, which is only
rabbinic. But if a non-Jew isn't entering the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash,
*Beis HaMikdash*, then any time a non-Jew's קרבן korban *korban* is brought,
he's not doing it himself, so the only person who could do
it would be somebody else. But that idea of a non-Jew not
entering the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beis HaMikdash* is only rabbinic.
They could go into עזרת נשים *Ezras Nashim*.
Right. But the סמיכה semichah, *smicha* was done in the עזרה *Azara*.
Yeah. Because במקום שסומכין במקום ששוחטין *bimkom shesomchim bimkom sheshochtim* is going
to be the next line.
So if I, if I send a, if I send a חטאת
chatas *chatas* with an agent as part of my שליח shaliach *shaliach*.
So we're going to discuss שליח shaliach *shaliach* in the next... Okay,
sorry. Not a problem.
I didn't read ahead.
Not a problem. Okay, קרבנו לרבות כל בעלי קרבן korban, לסמיכה *Korbano
lerabot kol ba'alei korban lismicha*. If it is a קרבן korban. *korban*
in partnership, a couple of people jointly are bringing an עולה Olah
*olah* or a שלמים *shlamim*... you can't jointly bring a חטאת chatat
*chatas*, but if they're bringing an עולה Olah, *olah* or a שלמים
*shlamim*, so then how does it work? So then... This phrase is
ambiguous. It could mean that any one of them can do it
for the group, which is a little bit like we saw yesterday,
the idea of the כהן kohen. doing it for all of כלל
ישראל Klal Yisrael by the שעיר המשתלח. sa'ir hamishtaleach. Or as we're
going to see in the עמוד ב amud bet when it quotes
this line, it could mean the opposite. It could mean that they
all have to do it. You can't have one person represent the
group. They all have to do it. So this is a little
bit ambiguous what this line means. We'll see more about this on
the עמוד ב. amud bet.
So that that second one would be a good reason to not
do it for a פסח because you might have a big group.
Okay, but would it make it impossible and in a partnership קרבן,
korban, we'll see in a minute what what the I mean again
this line is a little vague. Here רש״י Rashi says it means
one person can represent the group, but when we read it on
the עמוד ב, amud bet, it's going to sound like it means
the opposite. So it's a little bit of an ambiguous statement. Okay,
so now the משנה Mishnah goes on: היורש סומך. hayoresh somech. Somebody
who inherits a קרבן korban can do סמיכה. semichah His father dies
and left leaving him with a קרבן. korban, So if it's a
type of a קרבן, korban now not a חטאת because a חטאת
if the person died, you have to let the חטאת die. An
אשם however, if the owner died, it gets if once it's set,
you know what you're supposed to do is wait for it to
get a מום mum and then transfer the money and bring an
עולה. Olah But if you accidentally שחטed shacht it after it was
designate put aside to get a מום mum and set out to
graze, then it would function as an עולה Olah and therefore as
an עולה Olah you do סמיכה. semichah So anything other than you
know that you're going to actually bring as an heir, you do
סמיכה semichah on. תני רבי חנינה קמיה דרבא. tani Rabi Chanina kamei
deRava. So רבי חנינה Rabi Chanina taught in front of רבא Rava
the following version of the ברייתא: braita: יורש אינו סומך יורש אינו
מימר. yoresh eino somech yoresh eino meimir. A יורש yoresh does not
do סמיכה. semichah. He had a different גרסא girsa in the משנה.
Mishnah A יורש yoresh does not do תמורה. tmura. Cannot obviously nobody's
allowed to do תמורה, tmura, but is it effective if you do?
And our משנה Mishnah says yes, and this version said no. So
רבא Rava said back to him: והנן תנן היורש סומך ומביא את
נסכיו וממימר. v'anan tnan hayoresh somech u'meivi et n'sachav u'meimir. Anyway, the
יורש yoresh does do סמיכה, semichah brings the נסכים and does תמורה.
tmura. So אמר ליה איפכא. amar lei ifcha. So he said to
רבא, Rava, so should I reverse it? Meaning is my version obviously
wrong because it's against the other version of the text? אמר ליה
לא. amar lei lo. No, don't reverse it. מתניתין matnitin or at
least it should be מתניתין, matnitin, probably to be מתניתין, matnitin, whatever
your ברייתא braita or
מתניתין matnitin anyway, who is it? רבי יהודה היא. Rabi Yehuda hi.
Your version of it that says that the יורש yoresh does not
do סמיכה semichah is רבי יהודה. Rabi Yehuda. There's actually two different
תנאיic tannai opinions. Our text of the משנה Mishnah is the opinion
that a יורש yoresh does סמיכה. semichah. Yours is the opinion that
a יורש yoresh does not do סמיכה. Semicha דתניא, detanya, we taught
in the ברייתא: braita: יורש סומך. yoresh somech. I'm sorry, I got
it wrong, it is מתניתין. matnitin. Our משנה Mishnah: is רבי יהודה.
Rabi Yehuda. Your your version is the opposing position. Our משנה Mishnah,
that says a יורש yoresh does סמיכה Semicha is
is רבי יהודה. Rabi Yehuda. דתניא, detanya, we taught in the ברייתא:
braita: יורש סומך יורש ממימר. yoresh somech yoresh meimir. No, I was
right the first time.
Okay. Last time I thought I made a mistake, I was wrong.
Okay, anyway so. Alright so okay the ברייתא braita your
it's מתניתין matnitin is a funny word because it means our math
you know anyway normally means our anyway פט. pat. Okay, fine. Back
to the way it was. Your version of the משנה Mishnah. is
רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda who says that a יורש yoresh does not
do סמיכה. Semicha דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא: braita: יורש
סומך יורש מימר. yoresh somech yoresh meimir. The first opinion is like
our משנה: mishna יורש yoresh does סמיכה, Semicha יורש yoresh does תמורה.
tmura. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabi Yehuda omer, and now here's an opposing
position. רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda says: יורש אינו סומך יורש אינו מימר.
yoresh eino somech yoresh eino meimir. יורש yoresh does not do סמיכה,
Semicha. does not do תמורה. tmura. And therefore your version of אינו
סומך אינו מימר eino somech eino meimir was רבי יהודה. Rabi Yehuda.
Now we're going to look at this debate.
מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה? mai ta'ama deRabi Yehuda? What's the reasoning of
רבי יהודה? Rabi Yehuda? Going back to the פסוקים psukim yet before
of putting your hands על ראש rosh קרבנו, his
קרבן. korban? קרבנו ולא קרבן אביו. v'lo korban aviv. It has to
be yours, not your father's. So therefore it's not if you don't
really, it's not fully your קרבן. korban You're in enough yours that
you inherited it and you can bring it, but not enough yours
that it's the one that you sanctified or that's coming for some
personal obligation of your own. You don't have enough of a connection
to it that you are entitled
to do תמורה, tmura, that you are entitled to do do סמיכה.
Semicha And therefore ותחלת הקדש מסוף הקדש, u'tchilat hekdesh misof hekdesh, you
learn the act of sanctifying from the what comes at the end
of the process. The end of the process is putting your hands
on סמיכה. Semicha. So the beginning of the process is sanctifying. But
of course you can sanctify if you're an heir of things you
inherited, but what you can't do is transfer קדושה kdusha, of some
of a קרבן korban that you inherited.
ותחלת הקדש מסוף הקדש: u'tchilat hekdesh misof hekdesh: מה סוף הקדש יורש
אינו סומך, mah sof hekdesh yoresh eino somech, the same way at
the end the heir cannot do סמיכה, Semicha אף תחלת הקדש af
tchilat hekdesh at the beginning of the process יורש אינו מימר. yoresh
eino meimir. He cannot do תמורה. tmura. Now again, nobody's allowed to
do תמורה, tmura, but it means it's not effective. Now תוספות Tosafot
has a long תוספות tosafot in saying there are many ways in
which we distinguish between סוף הקדש sof hekdesh and תחלת הקדש. tchilat
hekdesh. There are many things that are not parallel. But תוספות tosafot
says the point here is not just an arbitrary saying if it
works at the end it works at the beginning or vice versa.
What we're saying it means is that are you considered the owner?
It's a specific question where the idea of ownership is what is
significant. So to transfer the קדושה, kedusha again it's funny because it's
not allowed, but nevertheless if I try to do תמורה tmura on
your animal, it wouldn't be effective and it wouldn't even be considered
an act of תמורה tmura because I'm just a stranger off the
street. My attempt to to transfer קדושה kedusha is meaningless. So to
have a role to be transferring קדושה kedusha, even though you're transgressing
and then it's effective is only if you have a certain relationship
to this. So what the question is, if you would, this is
this interesting issue that we've dealt with before, the difference between monetary
ownership over the animal and its sort of intrinsic קדושה, kedusha, its
sanctity in terms of its purpose, not in terms of its ownership.
So on the one hand you're an heir and you inherited as
a piece of property. On the other hand it has a קדושה,
kedusha, which is not something that you've created and does not link
to you. So to what degree does the fact that now you've
inherited this property also link its קדושה, link its identity as a
קרבן korban, to you? So Rabbi Yehuda is saying, it does not.
קרבנו and not that of an heir. And since it is not
linked to you, to the heir, you cannot do סמיכה, Semicha. which
is about relationship, and you cannot do תמורה, tmura, which also relates
to the relationship and being able to call it your קרבן. korban
That's what Rabbi Yehuda says. You cannot do either.
Okay. So ורבנן ve-rabbanan and the Rabbis they say no, המיר ימיר
ואם המיר ימירו אותה, hemir yamir ve-im hemir yamiru otah, if he
shall do תמורה, tmura, the double language is inclusive לרבות את היורש,
lerabbot et hayoresh, means that it's a more inclusive
category, anybody, not anybody, but even a bigger group can do תמורה,
tmura, even the heir. And now if the heir can do תמורה,
tmura, so we go the opposite, ויליף סוף הקדש מתחילת הקדש, ve-yalif
sof hekdesh mi-tchilat hekdesh, we learn the end of the process from
the beginning. מה תחילת הקדש יורש מימר, ma tchilat hekdesh yoresh meimir,
the same way at the beginning of the process you're considered an
owner that you can do תמורה, tmura, אף סוף הקדש יורש סומך,
af sof hekdesh yoresh somech, at the end of the process heir
does סמיכה. Semicha So again, as תוספות Tosafot says, it's not just
an arbitrary learning beginning from end, it's a fundamental question of to
what degree can we call it your קרבן. korban You've inherited it
as property, but you didn't sanctify it. So to what degree can
we call it your קרבן, korban, Rabbi Yehuda says not so much,
so you can't do סמיכה, Semichah. you can't do תמורה, tmura, and
the חכמים chachamim say yes we can call it your קרבן korban
and you can do both. Okay. So now the Gemara says like
this, now it just has to finish up working about what we
do with all the פסוקים. ורבנן
האי קרבנו מאי עבדי ליה, ve-rabbanan hai korbano mai avdi leh, since
they don't learn קרבנו to exclude the heir, what do they use
from the ו vav, of the קרבנו? Yours and not somebody else's.
מאי עבדי ליה קרבנו ולא קרבן עובדי כוכבים קרבנו ולא קרבן חבירו
קרבנו לרבות כל בעלי קרבן לסמיכה, mai avdi leh korbano velo korban
ovdei kochavim korbano velo korban chaveiro korbano lerabbot kol baalei korban lismicha,
like we said before, to exclude that who does not do סמיכה,
Semichah you don't do סמיכה Semichah on somebody else's, a non-Jew doesn't
do סמיכה, Semichah, and if it's a group, either one person does
it for the group or all the people of the group have
to do it. Okay. So that's what he learned, they learned from
the ו, vav but not to exclude the heir. ורבי יהודה לרבות
כל בעלי קרבן לסמיכה לית ליה, ve-rabbi yehuda lerabbot kol baalei korban
lismicha leit leh,
what does Rabbi Yehuda do? He needs one of those קרבנו to
exclude the heir. So either he disagrees with this idea of a
group, and he would say by the group, again it's funny because
we don't know what the תנא קמא tanna kamma is saying. Let's
assume the תנא קמא tanna kamma is saying based on the next
Gemara that if it's a group every member of the group has
to do it. So Rabbi Yehuda wouldn't agree with that and he
might say that one person of the group could do it. So
either there and therefore he has an extra קרבנו to exclude the
heir,
ואינמי אית ליה עובדי כוכבים וחבירו מחד קרא נפקא, ve-einami ait leh
ovdei kochavim ve-chaveiro mi-chad kra nafka, oh, I said before it's Rashi,
it turns out it's the Gemara. All right, anyway, so, so he
learns out to exclude the non-Jew and not your own קרבן korban
from the same פסוק, pasuk because with the assumption that the non-Jew
would never be bringing his קרבן Korban into the בית המקדש, Beit
Ha-Mikdash somebody else would have to bring it, so then it automatically
is the problem of not doing סמיכה, Semichah. somebody else doing סמיכה
Semichah on your קרבן. Korban So you don't need two פסוקים, you
have an extra קרבנו to exclude the heir. יאתו ליה תרי קראי,
yatu leh trei karai, so now he has two פסוקים left over,
חד קרבנו ולא קרבן אביו, chad korbano velo korban aviv, one to
exclude the heir, ואידך לרבות כל בעלי קרבן לסמיכה, ve-idach lerabbot kol
baalei korban lismicha, to say that if it's owned in partnership, everybody
has to do it and it's not one person doing it for
the group. ורבי יהודה האי המיר ימיר מאי עביד ליה, ve-rabbi yehuda
hai hemir yamir mai avid leh, now that's how we dealt with
the extra קרבנו or how we learned from קרבנו to exclude the
son. For
Rabbi Yehuda now, what does Rabbi Yehuda do with the double language
of המיר ימיר, hemir yamir, which the חכמים chachamim learned to say
that even an heir does
סמיכה? Semichah מיבעי ליה לרבות את האשה, miba'ei leh lerabbot et ha-isha,
that a woman can do תמורה, tmura, דתניא, de-tanya,
now why would I think not? I mean, you know, woman owns
property, makes קרבנות, brings קרבנות, why would I think not? So let's
take a look. דתניא לפי שכל הענין כולו אינו מדבר אלא בלשון
זכר, de-tanya lefi she-kol ha-inyan kulo eino midaber ella bilshon zachar, the
whole פרשה parsha is all in the male, you know, it's המיר
ימיר hemir yamir and it's always in the male, I mean almost
every פרשה parsha in the תורה torah is in the male. So
מה סופנו לרבות את האשה, ma sofenu lerabbot et ha-isha, how do
we know we're able to include even a woman that she does
תמורה, tmura, she makes תמורה? tmura? Again, not that it's allowed, but
she's prohibited and if she does it it's effective. תלמוד לומר המיר
ימיר, talmud lomar hemir yamir, the double language. ורבנן דרשי מן ואם,
ve-rabbanan darshi min ve-im, the extra ו and the if, that includes
even a woman. ורבי יהודה ואם לא דריש, ve-rabbi yehuda ve-im lo
darish, again, he's not impressed with that word, he needs to learn
it from the double language. Now, this leads to a very interesting
תוספות Tosafot who basically says, look, every single פרשה parsha of the
תורה torah is in the male. And we basically assume that women
are included, you know, so do we normally assume women are included
by the language of the male, do we normally assume they're excluded,
why did we need a ריבוי, ribui, and תוספות Tosafot basically says
I'll try to read the key line here.
One minute.
Okay, so he quotes the גמרא בתמורה, Gemara be-Temurah, it's not such
a satisfying answer but he quotes the גמרא בתמורה Gemara be-Temurah that
says that because this is a type of thing that other people
are excluded from, like for example we know that there's no תמורה
Temurah by קרבן ציבור Korban Tzibbur or there's no תמורה Temurah by
קרבן Korban of שותפים. shutafim. So since it's not applied completely universally
across the board, I might have chosen, I might have read the
פסוק pasuk. in a more exclusionary way. If you want to see
where he says it, he quotes the גמרא בתמורה, Gemara be-Temurah, it's
about eight lines from the bottom of the before I mean eight
lines before the lines get wide. He says like this: היינו טעמא
דמפרש בתמורה מהו דתימא הני מילי עונש דשוה בין ביחיד בין בציבור.
Hainu ta'ama de-mefaresh be-Temurah mahu de-teima hani mili onesh di-shaveh bein be-yachid
bein be-tzibbur. When do we assume women are the same? For things
that are like prohibitions and that are equal, that apply universally. אבל
הכא כיון דעונש אינו שוה בכולם, Aval hacha kivan de-onesh eino shaveh
be-kulam,
it's not universal, דהא אין הציבור והשותפין עושים תמורה, de-ha ein ha-tzibbur
ve-ha-shutafin osim Temurah, that if it's a communal קרבן Korban or a
partnership קרבן, Korban you can't make תמורה, Temurah, אשה נמי כי עבר
לא תלקי, Isha nami ki avar lo tilki, so maybe wouldn't transgress,
wouldn't get מלקות malkot or wouldn't be effective, קמשמע לן. kamashmalan.
So that's his explanation. Again, not fully satisfying, but at least saying,
you know, if there's a reason that it's not universal, then we
wonder whether the male is to be interpreted specifically. Now again, that's
only to explain why we needed the extra פסוק. pasuk In the
end, of course, there's not a good reason to exclude women, so
the extra פסוק Pasuk? comes to include, but why it was needed
is, you know, when something is not fully universal, then we start
wondering how to interpret the male language. So that is actually a
good segue into the next משנה, mishna, I see Rivka's already getting
upset, which is going to be whether women do סמיכה, Semichah because
this was about תמורה, Temurah, we say women do תמורה, Temurah, but
now we're going to talk about whether women do סמיכה, Semichah so
let's take a look at the next משנה. mishna Okay, הכל סומכין,
Hakol somechin, everybody does סמיכה, Semichah so now we finished talking about
which קרבנות, now we talk about the act, now we talk about
who does it. All do סמיכה, Semichah חוץ, with the exception of
חרש שוטה וקטן, Cheresh Shoteh ve-Katan, people that are not, you know,
considered of mature mind, either, you know, of mental capacity, or adulthood
in the case of the קטן, katan, וסומא, ve-sumah, a blind person,
ועובד כוכבים, ve-oved kochavim, a non-Jew which we had mentioned before, והעבד,
ve-ha-eved, a slave, והשליח, ve-ha-shaliach, an agent. So that goes to the
issue about when it says you and not קרבן Korban חבירו, it's
excluding even somebody who's designated as an agent. You have to do
it for yourself. It's very much about the personal connection to the
קרבן. Korban. והאשה, ve-ha-isha, and a woman. וסמיכה שירי מצוה, ve-semichah she'arei
mitzvah, סמיכה Semichah. is the remnant of the מצוה, mitzvah, which means
that if you don't do it, you're still יוצא. yotzei. Okay, the
גמרא, Gemara that's a phrase that the גמרא Gemara. uses also by
the waving and other things which are important for the full effect
of the קרבן, Korban but בדיעבד bedieved you're יוצא. yotzei. על הראש,
al ha-rosh, you do it on the head of the animal, בשתי
ידים be-shtei yadayim with both fingers, ובמקום שסומכין שוחטין, u-ve-makom she-somechin shochtin,
you do the סמיכה Semichah. right where right in the same place
you're going to do the שחיטה, shechting ותכף לסמיכה שחיטה, ve-teikef li-semichah
shechitah, as soon as you're done with the סמיכה Semichah, you שוחט
shecht it immediately. And the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to connect it too
because you שוחט shecht it immediately you have to do it in
the same place because you don't want to move it after you
did the סמיכה. Semichah Okay, so first let's focus on who is
excluded. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: בשלמא חרש שוטה וקטן
דלאו בני דעה נינהו. Bi-shlama Cheresh, Shoteh, ve-Katan de-lav bnei de'ah ninhu.
I understand the קרבן Korban of a חרש שוטה וקטן Cheresh Shoteh
ve-Katan because they are not people of intellect. Now I have to
tell you, to me that's not self-evident, because, you know, first if
they're bringing a קרבן, Korban. you could ask could you bring a
קרבן Korban for חרש שוטה וקטן Cheresh Shoteh ve-Katan and there's some
discussion maybe you can, like let's say somebody even sanctified... what?
A קטן katan brings a קרבן? Korban.
Well let's say for example somebody sanctified a קרבן korban, for his
sake, or let's take an easy case, let's take the case of
the חרש, Cheresh, let's say or the שוטה, Shoteh, let's say somebody
sanctified a קרבן korban. and then they had a psychotic episode and
during this psychotic episode and they're a שוטה, Shoteh, whatever, can you
bring a קרבן, korban, can you bring their קרבן korban? for them
when they are not of right mind? Okay, so, you know, maybe
like do you have to be of right mind when a קרבן
korban, is being brought to you for you to be יוצא? yotzei?
It's an interesting question like I mean I know we tend to
think yes because we tend to think about the whole תשובה Tshuvah
process and that's not what it's about, it's about חטא cheit and
so on but you know I mean but maybe the effectiveness of
the קרבנות maybe is not so much about the individual. What? Sorry?
So the way you set up our understanding of סמיכה smicha. to
this point was that it's more about that connection.
More connection. Correct. So that's what I think, I think that so
that's where I was going, which is if you just looked at
סמיכה smicha as some formal ritual right so then okay so who
cares they're not בני דעה. bnei de'ah. If you say בני דעה
bnei de'ah don't bring their קרבן, korban. don't tell me don't do
סמיכה. smicha Say you don't bring a קרבן korban of a חרש
שוטה וקטן. Cheresh Shoteh ve-Katan. This text suggests that you could imagine
bringing a קרבן korban for them that like I gave an example
they sanctified and now he's not of his right mind but nevertheless
סמיכה'ס semichah's not appropriate and you know I think what Ariel was
saying is exactly where I was headed that it's not just some
ritual, it's something about exactly that. It's not just a קרבן is
being brought for me, I'm oblivious, but somehow I get
some point in my credit. The whole idea of סמיכה smicha. is
the connection to the קרבן and that's not seen as meaningful if
you're not of right mind.
But any מצוה, Mitzvah, like why are you differentiating by the קרבן
and try to figure out the תשובה Tshuvah, thing and intention, any
מצוה Mitzvah is not...
Yeah, because here it's not a question about are you חייב Chayav
in מצוות, Mitzvot, but is the קרבן עולה Olah for
you? Are you... Here's an
example, right? Because the whole idea of קרבנות is very much that
somehow this ritual which you're not doing personally, right?
I understand, but you don't have to go there. You don't have
to go there regardless of the idea of the theology of קרבנות
and so on, but any any מצוה Mitzvah action is not valid
when done by חרש שוטה וקטן. Cheresh Shoteh ve'Katan.
Yes, but I'm not asking is it a מצוה. Mitzvah. Let's say
for example we say that let's take another theology: יסורין ממרקין. Yissurin
Memarkin. But let's say we say יסורין ממרקין. Yissurin Memarkin. So somebody
did a חטא Cheit in their right mind, then they became a
שוטה, Shoteh, and then that was part of their יסורין Yissurin anyway,
and then they suffered more יסורין. Yissurin. Would we say they don't
get כפרה Kaparah because they're not in their right mind? Maybe they
would. How do we know, right? So maybe if a קרבן is
brought for somebody when he's a שוטה, Shoteh, maybe it achieves כפרה
kaparah for the חטא, Cheit, maybe it gets him out of his
obligation. I'm not saying whether he's חייב Chayav in מצוות. Mitzvot. I'm
saying whether it's effective in terms of, you know, functioning as a
קרבן for that person.
Are we saying that the person himself, the חרש שוטה וקטן, Cheresh
Shoteh ve'Katan, can't do סמיכה smicha or that you can't do סמיכה
smicha on behalf of that person?
That you certainly can't do because that's קרבנו ולא קרבן חבירו, ולא
שליח. Velo Shaliach.
So then I don't understand why you're even investigating this because just
like a חרש שוטה וקטן Cheresh Shoteh ve'Katan putting on
תפילין Tefillin isn't effective or...
But there are places for example where a קטן... Katan... Right, you
can bring the
קרבן. For example there are places where an act of a קטן
Katan might be significant. Like if a קטן Katan does יבום, Yibum,
okay, it counts because that's about the physical act, that's not about
the intention. So there are times where these actions, right, so that's
basically where I'm going. But yeah, that's basically my point that it's
not just about the physical act here. Yeah, sorry.
If someone in their right mind designates an animal as a קרבן
and then they lose their mind and they become mentally incompetent, then
you have to deal with... and that קרבן can't be brought, you
have to deal with the question then of what happens to that
animal.
Right. Well, that's also what happens if somebody dies. You know what
happens, that's יורש Yoresh questions. So yes, those are issues that have
to be dealt with, right. Okay, so anyways the גמרא Gemara takes
that for granted that you don't do סמיכה smicha if you're not
בני דעה. Bnei De'ah. עובד כוכבים נמי, Nami, a non-Jew doesn't do
סמיכה. smicha, בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael it says, right, in the... it
says at the very beginning of ויקרא. Vayikra. What's the פסוק? Pasuk
דבר אל בני ישראל, Daber el Bnei Yisrael, I guess. Okay, anyway,
so בני ישראל סומכים ואין עובדי כוכבים סומכים. Bnei Yisrael Somchim ve'Ein
Ovdei Kochavim Somchim.
אלא סומא מאי טעמא, Ella Suma Mai Ta'ama, why a blind person
not? So מאי טעמא לא? Mai Ta'ama Lo? רב חסדא ורבי יצחק
בר אבדימי, Rav Chisda ve'Rabbi Yitzchak bar Avdimi, חד אמר, Chad Amar,
one says אתיא סמיכה סמיכה מזקני העדה. Atya Semicha Semicha mi'Ziknei ha'Edah.
It says by the elders of the where they do סמיכה smicha
by the... what do you call it? By the פר העלם דבר
Par Helam Davar where they do סמיכה. smicha So it says that
and we know that a סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, members of סנהדרין Sanhedrin cannot
be blind. So therefore there, since their סמיכה smicha nobody can be
blind, we apply it even by an individual סמיכה. smicha וחד אמר,
Vechad Amar, the other says אתיא סמיכה סמיכה מעולת ראיה. Atya Semicha
Semicha mi'Olat Re'iyah. No, because we learn it out from the individual
who brings an עולה, Olah. יראה כל זכורך, Yira'eh Kol Zechurcha,
right, on the שלושה רגלים Shlosha Regalim you're supposed to appear in
the בית המקדש, the males, and they bring a קרבנות, עולת ראיה.
Olat Re'iyah. And there the גמרא makes a famous
דרשה: Drasha: יראה יראה. Yira'eh Yireh. So the same way it says
you should appear in the בית המקדש, you also have to be
able to see. כשם שבאים ליראות כך באים לראות. Keshem sheBa'im lera'ot
kach ba'im lirot. They're coming to be seen,
they're coming to see. And therefore if they're blind even in one
eye, you don't have a מצוה Mitzvah of עולת ראיה. Olat Re'iyah.
And therefore, so there, the same way that that עולה Olah we
know the only people doing סמיכה smicha? are people with sight in
both eyes, so therefore we would say by all other סמיכות Semichot
it would only be people who are fully sighted. תוספות Tosafot points
out the problem that, in none of these cases do we learn
out anything else from them. We don't learn out any of the
other criteria about עולת ראיה Olat Re'iyah or any of the other
criteria of סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. We only learn out this one thing. תוספות
doesn't really know why we've chosen to learn out this one thing.
I will say something about the יראה יראה, Yira'eh Yireh, I actually
happened to speak about this over שבועות, Shavuot, which is that the
simple read of the פסוק Pasuk actually is יראה, Yireh, not יראה.
Yira'eh. יראה Yira'eh seems to be a euphemistic read of the
פסוק Pasuk because
יראה את פני השם אלקיך, Yireh et pnei Hashem Elokecha, את Et
designates the object of the verb, right? So you cannot be seen
את פני השם אלקיך. Et pnei Hashem Elokecha. If it was יראה
Yira'eh it would be לפני השם אלקיך. Lifnei Hashem Elokecha. את פני
Et Pnei means the seeing is being done to, את Et designates
the object of the verb. So really פשט Pshat of the פסוק
Pasuk is יראה את פני השם אלקיך. Yireh et pnei Hashem Elokecha.
But that's a little too anthropomorphic, so we read it יראה פני.
Yira'eh pnei. But this דרשה Drasha actually restores that simple read. It
says כשם שבאים ליראות כך באים לראות. Keshem sheBa'im lera'ot kach ba'im
lirot. Anyway, so...
with the two eyes? What? With the two eyes?
He blind one eye. I think, yeah, I've tried to remember how
the גמרא learns it out, but it says אפילו באחת מעיניו. Afilu
Be-Achat Mei-Einav. I think it's by the same analogy. The same way
God sees you fully, you have to be able to see fully.
I have to check the גמרא, but I think it's by that
same parallel. What? In stereo. In stereo vision, right. With depth perception.
Okay. So the גמרא says like this: ולמאן דאמר מעולת ראייה מאי
טעמא לא יליף מזקני העדה? U-Le-Man De-Amar Me-Olat Re'iyah Mai Ta'ama Lo
Yalif Mi-Ziknei Ha-Edah? So if you learn it by עולת ראייה, Olat
Re'iyah, why not from the elders?
דנין יחיד מיחיד ואין דנין יחיד מציבור. Danin Yachid Mi-Yachid Ve-Ein Danin
Yachid Mi-Tzibur. We'd rather learn out from cases of individual קרבנות rather
than learning out from the, you know, from the פר העלם דבר,
Par He'elam Davar, which is a communal
קרבן. ולמאן דיליף מזקני עדה מאי טעמא לא יליף מעולת ראייה? U-Le-Man
De-Yalif Mi-Ziknei Edah Mai Ta'ama Lo Yalif Me-Olat Re'iyah? So if you're
going to learn it out from the case of the elders, why
not learn it out from the קרבן that's brought for appearing on
the רגל? Regel? דנין מידי דכתיב ביה סמיכה בגופה ממידי דכתיב ביה
סמיכה בגופה Danin Midi De-Ketiv Bei Semichah Be-Gufeh Mi-Midi De-Ketiv Bei Semichah
Be-Gufeh because by the פר העלם דבר Par He'elam Davar it explicitly
says that the elders do סמיכה. semicha. So therefore I can learn
out a law of סמיכה semicha. from that. לאפוקי עולת ראייה Le-Apokei
Olat Re'iyah and I don't want to learn it out from the
case of the
עולה, Olah, דהיא גופה מעולת נדבה גמרה. De-Hi Gufa Me-Olat Nedavah Gamrah.
It never explicitly says you do סמיכה semicha on the עולת ראייה.
Olat Re'iyah. It says you appear in the בית המקדש and then
I say, oh, well since it's an עולה Olah. and since I
already know by עולה Olah, you do סמיכה, semicha I know by
this עולה Olah, you do סמיכה. semicha So I'd rather not have
that as the source of a הלכה Halacha of סמיכה semicha that
doesn't even talk explicitly about סמיכה semicha there. דתני תנא קמיה דרבי
יצחק בר אבא ויקרב את העולה ויעשה כמשפט. De-Tani Tana Kameih De-Rabbi
Yitzchak Bar Abba: Va-Yakrev Et Ha-Olah Va-Ya'aseh Ka-Mishpat. So here it's, and
he brings forth the עולה olah and he does it as is
the law. So from there we say כמשפט עולת נדבה Ka-Mishpat Olat
Nedavah that you do by this obligatory, that you do just like
the law of the free-will עולה. olah. לימד על עולת חובה שטעונה
סמיכה. Limed Al Olat Chovah She-Te'unah Semichah. So this is actually, this
is talking about not actually about anything that applies in future generations,
it's talking about the עולה that was brought on the eighth day
of the מלואים, Miluim, but nevertheless it says you do it like
the law, so that teaches me that even though this is an
obligatory עולה, you do סמיכה semicha, on it just like you do
סמיכה semicha. on a free-will עולה. So I only learn out from
this פסוק Pasuk that, you know, it's only one step derived. First
I tell you you do סמיכה semicha on a free-will עולה, then
I derive that you do סמיכה semicha on an obligatory עולה, so
I don't want that to be the basis of a law of
סמיכה. smicha I'd rather it be in a פסוק pasuk that explicitly
talks about סמיכה. smicha Okay, so that excludes the blind, or maybe
even blind in one eye. תוספות discusses that based on the, based
on the link to this idea. Now again, you could say, you
know, that it is this sense of, this identification, you know, without
the sight, you know, although again it's really, it feels a little,
more than a little discriminatory towards blind people as though the point
is that they don't have sight so they're trying to access their
world through their other senses, and you know, maybe they do have,
their other senses are more powerful. But, you know, if I was
trying to speculate on the logic, I would say that if the
whole idea is to create a greater sense of identification, so if,
you know, you don't have the, the ability to create that through
sight, maybe it's assuming that's not meaningful to create that just through
the sense of touch. Although you could have argued the opposite. How
much more so can you use the sense of touch if you're
trying to create that. Yes, what did you want to say?
I just said, well there was the issue of blind men getting
עליות. Aliyot. Aha.
That has to be what you have to be able to have
the potential to read from the תורה, Torah, right?
Right. And actually it's interesting that you mention that because there's a
very powerful תשובה on that. I forget by whom, that basically says
that he initially thought that a blind person can't get an עליה,
Aliyah, and then he says, and now in my old age that
I've become blind, and it's like this very moving תשובה where he
says, should I be excluded from נחלת השם, Nachalat Hashem, and I
have to go back and he talks about what that feeling of
exclusion is like. So, you know, then- I
think blind people get עליות.
Aliyot. Right. Right. We basically פסקן, Pasken, and based on that תשובה
really, we basically פסקן Pasken we give blind people עליות. Aliyot.
Well, women are excluded altogether.
I know. And that, right.
And you know, so- Maybe someone to say that.
Exactly. Exactly. I'll show you that תשובה, you know. But again, it
also shows you that, you know, he wasn't able to be sensitive
to that until he experienced it himself. You know. Who was that
by? I don't know, I'd have to find it, I'll look it
up, I'll look it up. But if they do bring, if they
do סמיכה, smicha, it's okay? We're saying that?
Well, no. That gets to the discussion in חגיגה Chagigah about women,
about if you're not allowed to do סמיכה- smicha?
But they did it and they were permitted.
Right. So let's talk about it by the women. But again, that
was with a special, it was a debate on whether it was
with a special accommodation, like not בכל כחו, Be-Chol Kocho, you know,
because that was concern about the misuse of the קרבן. That is
a discussion that comes by women. Here it's saying you're not obligated.
With women in חגיגה, Chagigah, not here, you get the discussion of
was it allowed? Right. Right. That's what you get in חגיגה Chagigah
by women. You don't have that discussion here, but that would be,
it would raise the interesting question, right, maybe the same thing by
blind. Right.
But there's an additional thing that you're not supposed to עבודה Avodah
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, and this was done on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, so that if someone who isn't obligated does it, it
might be- No,
I think you're conflating the phrase עבודה בקדשים Avodah Be-Kodshim with the
עבודה avoda of יום טוב.
Yom Tov. What's the difference?
עבודה בקדשים Avodah Be-Kodshim specifically means like using, you know- using them
in some form of service, like you're resting your weight on them.
That is not an עבודה avoda in הלכות יום טוב. hilchos Yom
Tov. That's an עבודה problem in הלכות קדשים hilchos kodshim because you're
resting your weight on it. There's no יום טוב Yom Tov problem.
I mean, there's a דרבנן derabbanan problem about using בעלי חיים, baalei
chayim, but that's not, I think, what's being...
But the reason I said it was, I know the bread that
people have written, the fact that women were permitted to do it
shows that it was, even though לכתחילה lechatchila no, but they were
even permitted to be...
Right, but that's because of עבודה בקדשים, avoda bekodshim, but it's about
עבודה בקדשים avoda bekodshim not עבודה ביום טוב. avoda beYom Tov. I
think you might be conflating... But it was on... That was yes,
but I don't think that was the concern.
It was חגיגה. Chagiga.
I know, but I'm saying the concern was עבודה בקדשים, avoda bekodshim,
it wasn't עבודה ביום טוב. avoda beYom Tov. Okay, so let's take
a look at the משנה mishna, because now we're going to turn
to the women issue, but it's going to be a different focus
than the one in חגיגה, Chagiga, which you are turning us to.
והעבד והשליח והאשה, Veha'eved vehashaliach veha'isha, and the slave and the agent
and the woman cannot do סמיכה. So the גמרא is going to
interpret these as a group and assume what we're talking about is
not doing סמיכה for their own קרבן, but doing סמיכה for the
man's קרבן. So the person's slave can't represent him, his agent can't
represent him, his wife can't represent him. That's how it is reading
this and which makes sense based on the grouping.
That's not being discussed here.
Okay, so let's read it. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan.
ידו, Yado, his hand, ולא יד עבדו, velo yad avdo, not his
slave. ידו, Yado, ולא יד שלוחו, velo yad shlucho, not his agent.
ידו, Yado, ולא יד אשתו, velo yad ishto, not his wife. וכולהו
למה לי? Vekulhu lama li? Why do I need to exclude all
three? Aren't they all sort of grouped together? No, צריכא, tzricha, I
need. אי כתב רחמנא חד, Ei kesav rachmana chad, if God had
just written one, הוה אמינא, hava amina, I would have thought, למעוטי
עבד דלאו בר מצוה, lema'utei eved delav bar mitzvah, that excludes a
slave that is
not a בר מצוה. bar mitzvah. Right? A non-Jewish slave is only,
you know, is not obligated in a positive time-bound מצוות. mitzvos. And
so therefore that cannot, he cannot represent the man. אבל שליח דבר
מצוה הוא, Aval shaliach debar mitzvah hu, but a שליח who is
obligated in מצוה, mitzvah, ושלוחו של אדם כמותו, ushlucho shel adam kemoso,
and we generally have a principle that a person's agent is a
representative of himself, אימא לסמוך, eima lismoch, maybe he can do סמיכה.
ואי אשמעינן הני תרתי, Ve'ee ashmi'inan hani sarti, if it excluded those
two, דלאו כגופיה דמו, delav kegufayhu damu, we never consider them to
be like the person himself. A slave we consider to be like
his property, but we never consider it to be a part of
the man of the person himself. אבל אשתו דכגופו דמיא, Aval ishto
dekegufu damya,
but his wife that sometimes we consider his wife to be actually
like his very body, like his very self, אימא תסמוך, eima tismoch,
maybe she can do סמיכה for her husband. צריכא, tzricha, so you
need to exclude all three. Nobody other than the person himself. So
like what we say on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, אני ולא השליח,
ani velo hashaliach, אני ולא... אני הוא ולא אחר, ani hu velo
acher, so it has to be you personally. It is specifically about
your connection to the קרבן, nobody else, even though these are all
good candidates, can represent you. So רבקה, Rivka, I'm sorry to say
that we're not here actually talking about what I know you would
like to talk about, which is interesting that it's not even addressed
in the משנה, Mishna. is the question can a woman do סמיכה
on her own קרבן? Right? That is really the discussion that we
find in חגיגה, Chagiga, which
are the issues that you're turning us to.
It is odd that they're not bringing that. What? It is very
odd that this משנה Mishna is not from this...
it seems like it would be totally...
Well, you mean because it discusses the possibility of her doing it
for her husband? Yeah. Well, no, but the הוה אמינא, hava amina,
I'm not sure you can make that inference. The הוה אמינא hava
amina is that she could do it sort of as her husband,
as it were, you know, to represent her husband. But to do
it as a woman, right, to represent, that's sort of not, and
in the end woman, the wife is excluded. But that is the
discussion in חגיגה Chagiga based on a תוספתא, Tosefta, ספרא, Sifra, whether
נשים סומכות nashim somchos or נשים אינן סומכות. nashim einan somchos. But
yes, it's very bizarre that A, it's not in the משנה, mishnah.
and B, the גמרא doesn't even bother bringing it. Because while we're
discussing חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh vekatan, we're not talking about them
as representatives, we're talking about... and סומא, suma, so those are people
where we're talking about their own ability to bring. So it is
very... Now, you could make the argument along your lines, that if
it's saying הכל סומכין hakol somchin and it's only excluding a wife
as a representative, then she would be included in הכל. hakol. Right.
Right. Oh, is that what you meant? Okay. All right, then I
misunderstood what you meant. So that could be. So anyway, that is
the discussion in חגיגה, Chagiga, yes.
And back to what you're talking about earlier about what does this
סמיכה mean and what it was represent, if women who are, say
a woman who is obligated in a חטאת, for instance, and would
make, would ordinarily make a וידוי but can't do סמיכה, that would
have a different, that would imply that the סמיכה has some other
purpose than...
Well, you know, that is an excellent point, which I hadn't thought
about. But you're right. Normally, like, because the גמרות Gemaros about סמיכה
are about normally more like the שלמים and the עולה and the
יום טוב Yom Tov חטאת. But if you think about the חטאת
context and the where the סמיכה is wrapped up with the וידוי,
what does it mean to be removing the סמיכה there? And is
there discussion about the woman doing וידוי without doing the סמיכה? That's
a very good question. I'd have to look at that.
I'd have to...
I would have to look at that, yeah. I mean, I don't
remember there being... No, it's not discussed in the גמרא. I'm just
wondering if... Let me just take a quick look at the רמב"ם
I was looking at before. But that is a very good question.
There's enough there that if we were doing this today, you could
find an opening.
Right. In fact, in זבחים Zevachim we learn that a woman can
do the שחיטה shechita, of her own, of her—not even her own,
of anybody's.
Right. Let me just see.
Because
that was the hands-on experience when you brought a קרבן, right? Otherwise,
you just hand it over to the כהן. kohen, So this was
an individual—you could
participate.
Yes, anyone can do
the
שחיטה, shecht but I imagine that probably wasn't so common. I imagine
most people would do the סמיכה.
I would have
someone else do the
שחיטה for a large animal.
Yeah, they did all that. Yeah, the רמב״ם Rambam has no discussion
about what it means for the woman. And the רמב״ם Rambam includes
presumably the woman's exclusion in the, you know, in the סמיכה. In—well,
he says it's interesting, the way the רמב״ם Rambam brings it down
is he sort of reads it into the משנה. He says חוץ
מחרש שוטה וקטן ועבד ואשה וסומא ונכרי. chutz me'cheresh shoteh ve'katan ve'eved
ve'isha ve'suma ve'nochri. So he
does—and then he discusses ואין השליח סומך. ve'ein hashaliach somech. So the
רמב״ם Rambam chooses to read the אשה isha of the משנה as
being excluded even on her own sake and then discusses the שליח
as a second, as and as well, no agent, right?
Anyway, that's for more discussion when we do חגיגה. Chagigah. But it
is interesting that it is not here. Okay. סמיכה שירי מצוה. Semicha
she'yarei mitzvah. סמיכה is the remnant of the מצוה. mitzvah. תנו רבנן.
Tanu Rabbanan, וסמך ונרצה. Ve'samach ve'nirtzah. The פסוק pasuk says he should
סמיכה and then it will be for his, you know, it'll be
appeasement, it'll be accepted for him. וכי סמיכה מכפרת? V'chi semicha mechaperet?
So does סמיכה achieve this atonement? והלא אין כפרה אלא בדם, V'halo
ein kaparah ela b'dam, שנאמר, she'ne'emar, כי הדם הוא בנפש יכפר. ki
hadam hu banefesh yechaper. אלא לומר לך, Ela lomar lecha, it tells
you, שאם עשאה לסמיכה שירי מצוה, she'im asaa l'semicha she'yarei mitzvah, מעלה
עליו הכתוב כאילו לא כיפר.
ma'aleh
alav hakatuv k'ilu lo kiper.
If you made it like the remnant of the מצוה, mitzvah, meaning
you didn't bother doing it, then it's—the תורה Torah treats it as
if you did not get atonement. וכיפר, Ve'chiper, but nevertheless you did.
So you get like the bare bones atonement, but it is not
the full atonement. There's a level at which we say וסמך ונרצה
ve'samach ve'nirtzah that the כפרה kaparah requires this. But at the end
we'll say, you know, you will technically get כפרה kaparah. even without
this. And again, the more you see that סמיכה's about the sense
of identification, the more you understand the power of that in terms
of the issue of כפרה. And I suppose also the more you
understand what it means to be excluded from that, which gets back
to the issue of the women. So the גמרא says ותניא גבי
תנופה כי האי גוונא. v'tanya gabi tenufah ki hai gavna. Now we
see similarly by the waving. It says ותנופה לכפר. u'tenufah l'chaper. It
says you shall wave it, this is the חזה chazeh and the
שוק, shok and it should for an atonement. וכי תנופה מכפרת? V'chi
tenufah mechaperet? Does that atone? והלא אין כפרה אלא בדם, V'halo ein
kaparah ela b'dam, שנאמר, she'ne'emar, כי הדם הוא בנפש יכפר. ki hadam
hu banefesh yechaper. It's with the blood. אלא לומר לך, Ela lomar
lecha, שאם עשאה לתנופה שירי מצוה, she'im asaa l'tenufah she'yarei mitzvah, if
you made the תנופה tenufah into like some remnant of the מצוה,
mitzvah, you did not do it, מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו לא כיפר.
ma'aleh alav hakatuv k'ilu lo kiper. It's treated as if you did
not achieve atonement, but nevertheless וכיפר, v'chiper, you did, bare bones technically
get atonement. Now, I have to tell you, it seems that that's
a much more, you sort of, meaningful thing to say by the
סמיכה than by the תנופה. tenufah. Because the סמיכה, again, the way
I'm understanding it, it's all about designating the purpose of it, verbally,
mentally connecting to it, physically connecting to it. You can understand how
the whole experience is very different if you're not doing the סמיכה.
The תנופה tenufah is like, yes, it's giving the חזה and the
שוק shok to the כהן, kohen. and maybe also somehow maybe designating
them even more to God in some way, but that's not the
עיקר ikar function of the קרבן. The עיקר ikar function of the
קרבן is about the שלמים, it's not about the חזה and the
שוק going to the כהן. So it's funny the weight that that
is given in terms of the תנופה. tenufah.
When you do סמיכה on a human being, you're transferring, right? Like
with the כהנים or whatever.
Yes, there is some sense of a transfer of authority.
ונתת מהודך עליו
ve'natatah
me'hodecha alav and so on. So you could have said by the—that's
true, meaning I was—yeah, go ahead, say it.
You're transferring part of yourself.
Right. So you could have said, I—I alluded to that before, but
you're absolutely right. Meaning, before I said like especially if you think
about the סמיכה by the scapegoat, by the שעיר לעזאזל, se'ir la'azazel,
you're transfer—ונתת את כל עונות, ve'natata et kol avonot, you know, you
put the sins on the head. And you could certainly say the
way the רמב״ן Ramban discusses what קרבנות symbolize when they're coming for
sin, that it's like they're a surrogate for you and it's like
I am being offered up and like I deserve to die because
of my sins, that it's somehow is really not just an ownership
identification, but almost as though this קרבן represents me. I was sort
of skirting that because
I
don't like that, and even if there's—and
we come up with this, right?
But also it doesn't fit the non-חטאת case. Meaning, you could say
that by the sin offerings. I'm not sure how you would sort
of suggest that idea by the שלמים and the עולה.
I'm like giving myself fully to God.
Almost. Okay. I mean, I understand, but I guess—I guess I find
that symbolism troubling. But yes. Yeah, that gets us back, that gets
us back to עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Right. Well, it gets us
back to learning something out from עקידת יצחק, Akeidat Yitzchak, you know,
that sense of as if you're offering. And by giving myself fully
to God. That's okay. I mean I understand, but I guess I
guess I find that symbolism troubling. But yes. Yes, that gets us
back, that gets us back
to עבודה זרה.
Right, well it gets us back to you learning something out from
עקידת יצחק, Akeidat Yitzchak, you know, that sense of as if you're
offering yourself. But you're right, that is certainly something, that is certainly
an important thing to be to be focusing on as you know
one of the possible symbolisms. Okay, על הראש, al harosh, you do
it on the head. תנו רבנן, ידו על הראש ולא ידו על
הצוואר, yado al harosh velo yado al hatzavar, on the head and
not on the neck, וידו על הראש, veyado al harosh, on the
head, ולא על הגביים, velo al hagabayim, not on the back, ידו
על הראש, yado al harosh, on the head, ולא ידו על החזה,
velo yado al hachazeh, not on the chest. Okay, so גמרא says:
כל הני למה לי, kol hani lamah li, why do I need
all to include all of these? צריכא, tzericha, I need. דאי כתב
רחמנא חד, di katav rachmana chad, if it had just said once,
על הראש, al harosh, on the head, סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daatach
amina, ומעוטי צוואר, umiutey tzavar, I would have said it excludes the
neck, דלא קאי בהדי ראשא, delo qai bahadey rosha, that that's not
sort of at the same plane as the head, right, because the
neck is assumed to be either the underpart of the neck or
the sides of the neck. בהדי ראשא. Bahadey rosha. אבל גבו, Aval
gabo, the back, which would also include the back of the neck,
not the sides or the throat, אבל גבו דקאי בהדי ראשו, aval
gabo dekai bahadey rosho, that maybe it's an extension of the head
and it's at the same plane of the head, אימא לא, eima
lo, maybe that wouldn't be excluded. צריכא, tzericha, so it has to
say the ראש again to exclude even the you know the top
side of the neck and the back. ואי אשמעינן הני תרי, ve'ei
ashmi'inan hani tray, if it had just excluded these two, משום דלא
אשתרבו לתנופה, mishum delo ishtrabi letnufa, they're never waved, so here's again
somehow bringing סמיכה and תנופה tnufa together although תנופה tnufa is very
limited to the case of שלמים. אבל חזה, Aval chazeh, but the
chest, דאשתרבי לתנופה, de'ishtrabi letnufa, that is waved, at least with some
קרבנות, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe סמיכה would be acceptable there, צריכא,
tzericha, so it has to exclude all three. Okay, איבעיא להו, itba'ei
lehu, they raised the question: ידו על הצדדים מהו, yado al hatzdadim
mahu, what about on the side of the head, meaning like on
the cheeks? Would that be considered on the head? Okay, so says
מהו. mahu. תא שמע, Tashma, come and hear, and here's a תניא.
tanya. אבא בירא בשם רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר, Abba Bira beshem
Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov omer, so אבא בירא Abba Bira in the
name of רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov says: ידו
על הראש ולא ידו על הצדדים. yado al harosh velo yado al
hatzdadim. Okay, so he understands that one of the things being excluded
is also the side of the head, meaning the cheeks. בעי רבי
ירמיה: Ba'ei Rabbi Yirmiyah: מטלית מהו שתחצות, matli'at mahu shetachatzot, is there
a concept of a חציצה? chatzitza? Can you have a towel, some
type of a rag between your hands and the head of the
animal? So תא שמע, tashma, come and hear, ובלבד שלא תהא דבר
חוצץ בינו לבין הזבח, uvilevad shelo tehei davar chotzetz beino levein hazavach,
we have a ברייתא braita that says that it has to be
directly touching which makes sense, and there cannot be some חציצה chatzitza
between the two. Okay, let's just finish up to the משנה. ובשתי
ידיים, Uvish'tei yadayim, both hands. מנלן הני מילי, Minan hani mili, and
with all of your strength.
How do you know this? אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, אמר
קרא, amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says: וסמך אהרן את שתי ידיו,
vesamach Aharon et shtei yadav, and Aaron shall rest his two hands.
This is by יום כיפור. כתיב ידו, Ketiv yado, it's written ידו
yado in
the singular, וכתיב שתי, veketiv shtei, and it says two, and that's
why we read it שתי ידיו, shtei yadav, not שתי ידו. shtei
yado. זה בני אב, Zeh bney av, this is a paradigm. כל
מקום שנאמר ידו, Kol makom shene'emar yado, whenever it says ידו, yado,
even when we read it as the singular, here we read it
as the plural, but whenever it's written ידו, yado, הרי כאן שתיים,
harei kan shtayim, it really means both hands. עד שיפרט לך הכתוב
אחת, Ad sheyafrit lecha hakatuv achat, until it explicitly says one. So
from here we learn שתי ידיו, shtei yadav, the word ידיו yadav
can mean even both hands. And therefore whenever it says סמיכה, וסמך
ידו, vesamach yado, what's the פסוק pasuk by סמיכה? It is written
in the singular. So you have to admit that it is a
big חידוש chiddush to say you need both hands because the פסוק
says וסמך ידו, yado his hand, but we're saying no hand means
two hands. Okay, so that is what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says.
Now we're going to have an interesting story. אזל רבי אלעזר, Azal
Rabbi Elazar, so רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish student,
went, אמר לה שמעתא בבי מדרשא, amar leh shemaitah be'vei midrasha, he
told over this teaching in the בית מדרש. beit midrash. Wow, that's
a great דרשה, drasha, now we know how you learn out the
idea of both hands. But there was a little problem. ולא אמר
משמיה דריש לקיש, Velo amar mishmei de'Reish Lakish, he didn't give ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish credit, tell people ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said that.
שמע ריש לקיש, Shama Reish Lakish, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish heard about
this, ואיקפד, ve'ikped, he got upset, and he took umbrage. אמר ליה,
Amar leh, so now he is going to like show up רבי
אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, you know, in right to as a payback. אמר
ליה, Amar leh, he said to him: One minute, you're going around
telling everybody oh ידו yado means two, and you're not giving me
credit. So you are taking ownership of this, you're taking ownership of
this דרשה, drasha, let me ask you some questions. So he said
to him: אי סלקא דעתך כל היכא דכתיב ידו תרתי נינהו, iy
salka daatach kol heicha dekativ yado tarti ninhu, if every time it
says ידו yado? it means two, למה לי למכתב ידיו ידיו, lamah
li lemichtav yadav yadav, why does the תורה Torah ever say the
word ידיו yadav in the plural? אחלי עשרים וארבע ידיו, Achlei esrim
ve'arba yadav, he asked him twenty-four times the תורה Torah said ידיו
yadav in the plural. ידיו תביאנה, Yadav tevi'ena, ידיו רב לו, yadav
rav lo, שיכל את ידיו. shikel et yadav. So why does it
say ידיו yadav in all of these times if you could have
said ידו? So you know you should know the answer because you're
taking credit for this דרשה. drasha. אישתיק, Ishtik, he was silent. ובתר
דנח דעתיה, Ubatar de'nach daiteh, so then after ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
cooled off, this really shows like the passion of ריש לקיש, Reish
Lakish, you know, those whole stories about him being a bandit or
whatever. It also reminds you about how רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, you
know, moaned the death of ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, because when he
was in the בית מדרש beit midrash and he was teaching and
somebody says oh yes and I have a ראיה rayah to you
and oh yes and I have a ראיה rayah to you he
says oh. Anyway, alright, so anyway after ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish* calmed
down, אמר ליה *amar lei*, מאי טעמא *mai ta'ama* לא תימא לי
*lo teima li*, what you should have said to me was ידא
דסמיכה *yada d'smicha* קאמרי *ka'amri*. So that when I, my דרשה *drasha*
was not that every time it says ידו *yado* in the singular
it means two, but when it says ידו *yado* in the context
of סמיכה *smicha* which was the case by אהרן *Aharon*, that's where
it means two. So therefore it does not have to say ידיו
*yadav* because in the context of סמיכה *smicha* ידו *yado* means two.
So הגמרא *haGemara* says, "One minute, בסמיכה *b'smicha* נמי *nami* כתיב *ksiv*
ויסמוך את ידיו עליו ויצוהו *Vayismoch es yadav alav vayitzaveihu* by יהושע
*Yehoshua*. Why does it say in the plural?" No, סמיכה דבהמה *smicha
d'behema* קאמרי *ka'amri*. When it talks about doing סמיכה *smicha* on animals,
so my דרשה *drasha* is in a very limited context. When it
says ידו *yado* in the singular by סמיכה *smicha* in animals it
means two and therefore it never has to say ידיו *yadav*. Okay,
just to finish up to the משנה *Mishna*. ובמקום שסומכין שוחטין *ubemakom
shesomchin shochtin* תכף לסמיכה שחיטה *techef l'smicha shechita*. So you do שחיטה
*shechita* where you do the סמיכה *smicha*, which would mean in the
עזרה *Azara*, which gets back to the question about the women where
they would bring the animal to the עזרה *Azara* specifically and you
would שחט *shacht* immediately after סמיכה *smicha*. מאי קאמר *mai ka'amar*? What,
how is it related, you know, what's the relationship here? So הכי
קאמר *hachi ka'amar*: במקום שסומכין שוחטים *bemakom shesomchin shochtim*, you have to
do סמיכה *smicha* where you're gonna do the שחיטה *shechita*, why? שתכף
לסמיכה שחיטה *shetechef l'smicha shechita*, because you're gonna do the שחיטה *shechita*
immediately afterward. And therefore and again the power there is, you know,
whatever the relationship is being articulated through the סמיכה *smicha*, it immediately
now translates as and now the קרבן *korban* is being brought. You
know, so there's like it's juxtaposed so that relationship really defines now
the bringing of the קרבן *korban*. Okay, we continued on שבת *Shabbos*.